<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Cogitations of Topi</title>
    <link>https://kettunen.io/post.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Cogitations of Topi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Except as noted, this work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 13:35:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kettunen.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Leap of Faith in Email Providers</title>
      <link>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/24/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 13:35:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/24/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When talking about the tools of the trade, almost regardless of the
industry, email seems to be a vital tool. The same applies to
me. Obviously, in the tech industry, everything goes by email. But also
in music. If I happen to record, mix or master something, pretty much
always these are shared with email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email is also a crucial part of my workflow, so I care about my
productivity while using it. Recently I started to look for options for
my two different GSuite accounts. One of those was used for my personal
domain, and another one was used for my music publishing company. A big
reason behind the migration was that I found GSuite to be a little bit
too much for my needs. I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have anything against
Google&amp;rsquo;s product, albeit I agree they have a little bit too big of a
footprint on the internet, so I at least try to limit my contributions
to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements-for-provider&#34;&gt;Requirements for Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only have two requirements for my provider: IMAP/SMTP support and the
ability to use my domain(s). Given these requirements, there are
probably hundreds of providers that would fit these requirements. But
after a while of skimming through different providers, I ended up with
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastmail.com/&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://protonmail.com/&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fastmail&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail seemed like a good fit when I first looked into it. Easily
manageable domains and reasonable pricing. I quickly tested it with
their offered trial account and was overall pretty pleased with their
product. Concerns about this then rose when I learned that the company
is from Australia. Not that I hate Australia by any means, but their
hostile and subversive laws regarding encryption are pretty sketchy. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.homeaffairs.gov.au/about-us/our-portfolios/national-security/lawful-access-telecommunications/data-encryption&#34;&gt;The
assistance and access
act&lt;/a&gt;
allows, under Australia&amp;rsquo;s legislation, police to force companies to
create a technical function that would give them access to encrypted
messages without the user&amp;rsquo;s knowledge, which made FastMail pretty much a
no-go for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protonmail&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finding Australia&amp;rsquo;s laws against encryption, it seemed like a
natural choice. I had already heard of them before and their stand on
security. ProtonMail doesn&amp;rsquo;t support IMAP/SMTP access, at least in the
standard way, mainly because of encryption, which is why I didn&amp;rsquo;t want
to go that route when I first heard of them. Nowadays, they do offer a
kind of unorthodox solution for this via their ProtonMail Bridge. By my
understanding, this only handles the authentication to your mail and
provider localhost-only endpoints to IMAP4/SMTP. Then you can configure
your mail client of choice with these new endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting solution, and at least for me, it seems to work and doesn&amp;rsquo;t
hinder my workflow that much. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy
with their product and decided to migrate my emails to there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;honorable-mention-migadu&#34;&gt;Honorable Mention: Migadu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.migadu.com/index.html&#34;&gt;Migadu&lt;/a&gt;
Migadu is on the smaller end of the spectrum when talking about email
providers, but overall they seemed to have great values. Why I didn&amp;rsquo;t go
that route (yet?) is that I read that they have had some outages in
their services in the past. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that your email has been
lost since the global mail system is pretty tolerant for that, but not
being able to login into your mail, which can be pretty annoying. What
made them not very suitable for me is their bandwidth-based pricing and
daily limits on mail. I do work a lot with email and send and receive a
lot of them, so they did offer pricing suitable for my needs, but it
just was a little bit too expensive at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dishonorable-mention-self-hosting&#34;&gt;Dishonorable Mention: Self-hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail at first seemed like a good fit, but due to Australia&amp;rsquo;s
legislation, it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me. ProtonMail overall seems like
a pretty exciting provider, at least on paper and overall in practice too.
Service seemed to suite me, so I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to use their service at
least for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Comfy FreeBSD Jails Using Standard Tools</title>
      <link>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/17/standard-freebsd-jails.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 20:20:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/17/standard-freebsd-jails.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; has stormed into software development in
recent years. While the concepts behind it are powerful and useful, similar
tools have been used in systems for decades. FreeBSD&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/jails.html&#34;&gt;jails&lt;/a&gt; in one of those tools
which build upon even older &lt;code&gt;chroot(2)&lt;/code&gt; To put it shortly, with these tools, you
can make a safe environment separated from the rest of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jails in FreeBSD is by no means a new tool (introduced in 4.X), but for a reason
or another, I haven&amp;rsquo;t used them that often, which is a shame since they are so
powerful. So I wanted to explore this concept in a concise and summarized
manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;templates&#34;&gt;Templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZFS datasets are a great way of creating templates for jails since, after the
template creation, you can easily create new jails with &lt;code&gt;zfs clone&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;zfs send/receive&lt;/code&gt;. Typically people tend to divide jails to complete and service
jails, where the former usually resembles a real FreeBSD system, and the latter
is often dedicated to applications/services. I&amp;rsquo;ll cover complete jails for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The creation of templates starts with creating a dataset for your jail and
template. Here I&amp;rsquo;ll make a new dataset for the base installation of FreeBSD
12.2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo zfs create -o mountpoint=/vm zroot/vm
$ sudo zfs create zroot/vm/tmpl
$ sudo zfs create zroot/vm/tmpl/12.2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that, fetch the base installation itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ fetch ftp://ftp.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD/releases/amd64/12.2-RELEASE/base.txz
# Fetch all the necessary stuff for your template, e.g. lib32 if needed
$ sudo tar -xJvpf base.txz -C /vm/tmpl/12.2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that you should write a minimum viable &lt;code&gt;/etc/rc.conf&lt;/code&gt; for the template:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo emacs /vm/tmpl/12.2/etc/rc.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Refer to &lt;code&gt;rc.conf(5)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Start or stop services
sendmail_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
sendmail_submit_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
sendmail_outbound_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
sendmail_msp_queue_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
syslogd_flags=&amp;quot;-ss&amp;quot;
cron_flags=&amp;quot;-J 60&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also disable some unnecessary jobs for jails:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo emacs /vm/tmpl/12.2/etc/periodic.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Refer to &lt;code&gt;periodic.conf(5)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# No output for successful script runs.
daily_show_success=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
weekly_show_success=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
monthly_show_success=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_show_success=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
   
# Output to log files which are rotated by default.
daily_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/daily.log&amp;quot;
daily_status_security_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/daily.log&amp;quot;
weekly_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/weekly.log&amp;quot;
weekly_status_security_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/weekly.log&amp;quot;
monthly_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/monthly.log&amp;quot;
monthly_status_security_output=&amp;quot;/var/log/monthly.log&amp;quot;
   
# No need for those without sendmail
daily_clean_hoststat_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_status_mail_rejects_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_status_mailq_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_queuerun_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
   
# Host does those
daily_status_disks_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_status_zfs_zpool_list_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_status_network_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_status_uptime_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
daily_ntpd_leapfile_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
weekly_locate_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
weekly_whatis_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_chksetuid_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_neggrpperm_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_chkuid0_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_ipfwdenied_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_ipfdenied_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_ipfwlimit_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_ipf6denied_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
security_status_tcpwrap_enable=&amp;quot;NO&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You also might want to enable ports in your jail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo mkdir /vm/tmpl/12.2/usr/ports
$ sudo mkdir -p /vm/tmpl/12.2/var/ports/{distfiles,packages}
$ sudo emacs /vm/tmpl/12.2/etc/make.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;WRKDIRPREFIX = /var/ports
DISTDIR = /var/ports/distfiles
PACKAGES = /var/ports/packages
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apply system updates to the template:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo freebsd-update -b /vm/tmpl/12.2 fetch install
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, take a snapshot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo zfs snapshot zroot/vm/tmpl/12.2@complete
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This creates a snapshot of &lt;code&gt;zroot/vm/tmpl/12.2&lt;/code&gt; named &lt;code&gt;complete&lt;/code&gt;. You can then check your current snapshots with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo zfs list -t snapshot
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-jails-from-the-template&#34;&gt;Creating Jails from the Template&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you should be able to create a new jail based on that snapshot. You can do
it either with &lt;code&gt;zfs clone&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;zfs send/receive&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difference Between the Two&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A clone is a writable volume or file system whose initial contents are the
same as the dataset from which it was created. As with snapshots, creating a
clone is nearly instantaneous and initially consumes no additional disk
space. In addition, you can snapshot a clone.&amp;rdquo; [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The zfs send command creates a stream representation of a snapshot that is
written to standard output. By default, a full stream is generated. You can
redirect the output to a file or to a different system. The zfs receive
command creates a snapshot whose contents are specified in the stream that is
provided on standard input. If a full stream is received, a new file system is
created as well. You can send ZFS snapshot data and receive ZFS snapshot data
and file systems with these commands. See the examples in the next section.&amp;rdquo;
[2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo zfs clone zroot/vm/tmpl/12.2@complete zroot/vm/jail1

# OR

$ sudo sh -c &amp;quot;zfs send zroot/vm/tmpl/12.2@complete | zfs receive zroot/vm/jail1&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jail-configurations&#34;&gt;Jail Configurations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: These configurations is for very bare-bones jail, e.g. without any
mounts or advanced networking. Further configurations are discussed in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# /etc/rc.conf

cloned_interfaces=&amp;quot;lo0&amp;quot;

# PF is used for NAT and port forwarding.
pf_enable=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot;
pflog_enable=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot;

jail_enable=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot;
jail_list=&amp;quot;jail1&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Refer to &lt;code&gt;jail.conf(5)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# /etc/jail.conf

exec.start = &amp;quot;/bin/sh /etc/rc&amp;quot;;
exec.stop = &amp;quot;/bin/sh /etc/rc.shutdown&amp;quot;;
exec.clean;
mount.devfs;

host.hostname = $name;
path = &amp;quot;/vm/$name&amp;quot;;
exec.consolelog = &amp;quot;/var/log/jail_${name}_console.log&amp;quot;;
exec.prestart = &amp;quot;cp /etc/resolv.conf $path/etc&amp;quot;;
exec.poststop = &amp;quot;rm $path/etc/resolv.conf&amp;quot;;

jail1 {
        ip4.addr = &amp;quot;lo0|127.1.1.1/32&amp;quot;;
        ip6.addr = &amp;quot;lo0|fd00:1:1:1::1/64&amp;quot;;
        allow.chflags;
        allow.raw_sockets;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# /etc/hosts

...

127.1.1.1 jail1
fd00:1:1:1::1 jail1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jail-management&#34;&gt;Jail Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start/stop all jails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service jail start
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start/stop a specific jail(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo service jail start jail1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Log in to jail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo jexec jail1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exec a command on a jail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo jexec jail1 uname -a
FreeBSD jail1 12.2-RELEASE FreeBSD 12.2-RELEASE r366954 GENERIC  amd64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;List running jails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ jls
   JID  IP Address      Hostname                      Path
     3  127.1.1.1       jail1                         /vm/jail1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s how you can spin up a simple restricted environment on your FreeBSD
system. There are still lots of things to cover in this topic, e.g., in-depth
networking and configurations. But I think those deserve their own posts. So see
you soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Overview of ZFS Clones: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19253-01/819-5461/gbcxz/index.html&#34;&gt;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19253-01/819-5461/gbcxz/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Sending and Receiving ZFS Data: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E18752_01/html/819-5461/gbchx.html&#34;&gt;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E18752_01/html/819-5461/gbchx.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/jails.html&#34;&gt;FreeBSD Jails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reawakening Long Lost Habit (or Forming a New One)</title>
      <link>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/10/reawakening-long-lost-habit.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 18:03:57 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/10/reawakening-long-lost-habit.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I had a good habit of writing semi-regularly about
various exciting topics. Unfortunately, time passed, and I began to write less
and less, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten out of the habit altogether. This is a shame
in many ways since I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt writing to be immensely therapeutic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, this world is also in a very odd place. Most of the
countries worldwide are quarantined due to COVID-19, and people are staying in
their homes. Yours truly included! So as a way to pass the the time during these
times, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to reawaken this habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Habitual writing has been on my mind for a long time, especially since it has
been so present in my life before. I&amp;rsquo;ve also somehow lost a few other healthy
habits, which lately have made me think about how I can reawaken them in my
day-to-day life. Healthy practices that come to mind that I&amp;rsquo;ve lost would
definitely be workouts and meditation. Although you could argue that the lost
habit of working out is mainly related to the current difficult times, I&amp;rsquo;m not
too worried. That I believe that eventually, when the world calms down in terms
of this pandemic, I can relearn that habit quite quickly. But losing the regular
practice of meditation is really a shame, in my opinion. Similar to working out,
meditation has been playing a big part in my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though my meditation practices have been irregular lately, the earlier
&amp;ldquo;hard work&amp;rdquo; has definitely helped me in my everyday life. But recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve
started thinking about how I could relearn this habit. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that at
least in my own case best way to learn habit has definitely been doing something
often but not in an excessive amount. So in meditation, this was easy. Start by
5 or 10 minutes (which is nothing, and everyone can find time for this) and just
do it the same time and place every day. Current times supported in relearning
this since people are mostly working remotely, so it is easy to start your day
with this practice. With these simple steps, I feel like that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to
reawaken this practice that was once very present in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking about utilizing a similar approach in some other practices
that I&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten. The practices that came to mind were music and
writing. Although some could argue that these are more or less the same
thing. For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a real hard time picking up my instruments and
writing some new music during the pandemic. I believe that many others have the
same feelings in their own area of interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the cause for this;
maybe the constant staring at the same four walls for over a year is the
culprit. Who knows? A similar thing has also happened in my writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really got me wanting to reawaken these habits was when I stumbled upon
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dreamsongs.com/Bio.html&#34;&gt;Richard P. Gabriel&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; poetry. Gabriel is a
legendary Lisp programmer. As a Lisp programmer myself, I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in
what other like-minded people are up to. Gabriel started a project of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dreamsongs.com/DailyPoems.html&#34;&gt;writing
one poem a day on March 18, 2000&lt;/a&gt; to
end a lengthy poetry-writing slump. Gabriel agrees that he is not necessarily a
great poet, even though many could argue that, but I think that is
non-essential. While forming this kind of habit, you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to
be the new Robert Frost. But since writing poetry (or anything) is a technical
skill, constant practice is bound to help you in your journey. I stumbled upon a
similar approach while reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Writing-Better-Lyrics-Pat-Pattison/dp/1582975779&#34;&gt;Pat Pattison&amp;rsquo;s Writing Better
Lyrics&lt;/a&gt;,
where he talked about &amp;ldquo;daily object writing&amp;rdquo; in terms of getting better at
writing. Pattison also noted that forming a habit is the big thing in this,
which will eventually result in getting better at writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach is more or less similar to how I learned the healthy habit of
regular meditation. How could I apply a similar approach to my composing and
writing? Knowing myself, I cannot do this kind of creative work sporadically (or
waiting for the creative slump to end), or I&amp;rsquo;ll never do it. If I tried to write
one piece and post every day, I feel that doing both daily would be a little bit
excessive (mainly timewise). So I need to find a healthy balance in practice and
not making it over-encumbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I believe that some time-boxed, very focused practice on something
works the best. So what I&amp;rsquo;m intending to do is that I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on a period (half
an hour, an hour or so) on the given task, whether it is composing, writing, or
programming (another healthy habit that I practice which thankfully haven&amp;rsquo;t been
lost, but I always feel I could do more of it). I&amp;rsquo;ll set a healthy goal for this
time-box, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to write some new groundbreaking sonata, some
earth-shattering blog post, or the next big open source project. I&amp;rsquo;ll just want
to do something in these fields regularly to hone my skills in the given area. I
also understand that since I&amp;rsquo;m trying to work on multiple habits, I might not
always have time to do everything. That&amp;rsquo;s okay. I can most likely squeeze in a
smaller session so that you have at least some practice. Or if I just simply
cannot do anything, that&amp;rsquo;s fine too. I just don&amp;rsquo;t want to see myself doing
something excessively one day and then slacking off the next day since &amp;ldquo;I did so
much yesterday&amp;rdquo; (learned from Pattison).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity overall has been really close to my heart, even though I
occasionally lack significantly in that area. But maybe with small steps,
everyone can benefit somehow in a slight boost of their own productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or just procrastinate&amp;hellip; As long as you&amp;rsquo;re happy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
