<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Cogitations of Topi</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Cogitations of Topi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 20:20:26 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Creating Comfy FreeBSD Jails Using Standard Tools</title>
      <link>/post/standard-freebsd-jails/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 20:20:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/standard-freebsd-jails/</guid>
      <description>Docker has stormed into software development in recent years. While the concepts behind it are powerful and useful, similar tools have been used in systems for decades. FreeBSD&amp;rsquo;s jails in one of those tools which build upon even older chroot(2) To put it shortly, with these tools, you can make a safe environment separated from the rest of the system.
Jails in FreeBSD is by no means a new tool (introduced in 4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reawakening Long Lost Habit (or Forming a New One)</title>
      <link>/post/reawakening-long-lost-habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 18:03:57 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reawakening-long-lost-habit/</guid>
      <description>A couple of years ago, I had a good habit of writing semi-regularly about various exciting topics. Unfortunately, time passed, and I began to write less and less, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten out of the habit altogether. This is a shame in many ways since I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt writing to be immensely therapeutic.
At the time of writing, this world is also in a very odd place. Most of the countries worldwide are quarantined due to COVID-19, and people are staying in their homes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
