<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Topi Kettunen</title>
    <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Topi Kettunen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Except as noted, this work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 18:28:53 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://topikettunen.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Time Management and Balance With Multiple Passions</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/time-management-with-multiple-passions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 18:28:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/time-management-with-multiple-passions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always enjoyed reading about other peoples productivity hacks and
their workflows, in general, when it comes to whatever they might be
doing. I often stumble upon reading on how people manage to maintain an
extravagant lifestyle with dozens of different hobbies, interests, and
passions with ease. So it makes me wonder how they manage their time to
maintain a healthy level of participation in their interests without
burning out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have dozens of different passions or interests in my life, but
my passions tend to be quite large on their own, so when combining those
with 40 hour work week, I need to think about my time management
thoroughly. These passions I would consider to be writing, music and
programming.  Fortunately, I currently work in the tech industry, so I
can get a good living by doing one of my passions. Writing on its own
isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily a huge topic/interest, as it only consumes times, but
the practice itself is pretty straight forward. On the other hand, music
is time-consuming, and it involves many different activities in my
case. Sure, you could argue that writing does include other practices,
too, like planning what to write, but music is on another level for
me. I play multiple different instruments, which I record for myself and
others in my home studio. I enjoy composing tunes, add some mixing and
mastering to this, and you need to sacrifice a lot of time for
this. Programming is also something that I enjoy spending my time
on. While I do it for a living, what makes me truly like it are the
projects I work on in my free time, whether it&amp;rsquo;s my pet projects of
various sizes or some open-source projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the time and focusing on the task at hand isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily an
issue on its own for me, but its more about maintaining a healthy
balance between all these passions that I hold dear to me. Although that
being said, I would consider being a very gifted procrastinator, so
focusing on the task at hand can often be difficult for me. Once I&amp;rsquo;ve
gotten into the flow, focusing becomes no more an issue. A more
significant issue here is quite often finishing projects rather than
starting a new one (which I feel is entirely another issue to be
improved on).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I work on my passions, I tend to focus for days or weeks on one
passion, e.g. programming, neglecting my other passions like writing and
music. This on its own isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily a bad thing since I don&amp;rsquo;t feel
that I&amp;rsquo;m wasting my time when I&amp;rsquo;m doing something that I enjoy and
something where I&amp;rsquo;m able to get rewarded in multiple different ways. But
I would like to maintain an equal balance between my passions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools-to-the-rescue&#34;&gt;Tools to the rescue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I started reading about how other people have managed their
time with multiple different passions/hobbies, and almost unanimously,
everybody used various type of schedule for this. I have already used a
&amp;ldquo;life management&amp;rdquo; system for a long time to handle all my todo lists and
schedules related to my home and work life (insert praising words about
Emacs&#39; org-mode here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going into details about how I manage my life with org-mode,
but if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the tool, I would recommend going through
articles found at &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/worg/org-gtd-etc.html&#34;&gt;Org for GTD and other Task management
systems&lt;/a&gt; and from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sQS06Qjnkcc&amp;amp;list=PLVtKhBrRV_ZkPnBtt_TD1Cs9PJlU0IIdE&#34;&gt;Rainer
König&amp;rsquo;s OrgMode
tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I realize that has been missing for a long time in my current
setup is the fact that I haven&amp;rsquo;t scheduled when to work on what
project. While I&amp;rsquo;ve split my free-time projects into sub-tasks and
occasionally schedule and deadline when to work/finish those, the work
has always been very sporadic on this front. The result has often been
so that I work for an X period on one project then move on to another,
so I often just forget what I was supposed to do on the earlier
project. For me, this often leads to unnecessary postponing of tasks or
cancelling/removing them completely. I also quickly start saying that
&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll do it tomorrow&amp;rdquo;, which everyone knows won&amp;rsquo;t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-light&#34;&gt;Starting light&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how I started to approach the whole concept of time management
between multiple different interests was to make dedicated timeslots and
days for whatever I might be working on. I maintain numerous on-going
projects which don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have deadlines in them but are just
larger projects that I want to work on from time to time. Then these
projects have sub-projects which are usually scheduled with
deadlines. These projects and sub-projects might include something
related to work, home, open-source work, recording or simply just
writing something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I nowadays approach working these is by dedicating timeslots for
something on a specific day. My work life and day-to-day home stuff take
a good portion from my days, but the rest of the time, I try to use it
as efficiently as possible. So on Monday, I might work on some
programming related endeavours based on my backlog, Tuesday something
else and so on. The way I still approach tasks haven&amp;rsquo;t been changed in
any way, as in I still manage my tasks and TODOs and keep track of them,
but nowadays, I just dedicate specific days for specific
interest/passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel that I&amp;rsquo;m neglecting the stuff I want to work
on. Issues with this kind of approach are the context switching on
almost a daily basis. However, this kind of switching isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily
a bad thing. Personally, at least I don&amp;rsquo;t want to think about
work-related topics after I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;clocked in the hours&amp;rdquo;, but I want to do
something either to relax or to move my thoughts elsewhere. Issues that
I&amp;rsquo;ve mainly stumbled with are that when on one day you might focus on
programming, and the next day you focus on music. While this switch on
its own hasn&amp;rsquo;t been too bad in my case, but when I get back to, for
example, programming after doing something else for several days, it
always takes a while to get back to the flow. But I do believe that this
is just missing practice in the world of managing multiple different
passions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have now split my time between multiple passions for several weeks,
and I feel that this is an excellent way to go. It has also already
taught me about the stuff that I genuinely want to work with, since when
you write down what you want to do and when it&amp;rsquo;s easy to spot the stuff
that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to work on or just don&amp;rsquo;t have an interest about
it. So this also works in my case to find the topics that genuinely
interest me. Will I continue to manage my time like this for long? Well
hopefully. I feel that this way, I can contribute to all the stuff that
makes my life interesting, so obviously, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to miss that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI, Arts and the Future</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/arts-and-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 20:52:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/arts-and-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the discussion about artificial intelligence has become
mainstream, I have started to ponder the possible impacts AI might have
on our day-to-day lives. While I work in tech, I come from this &amp;ldquo;culture
and arts&amp;rdquo; background at least a little bit. I did some theatre when I
was young and also have worked with music in one way or another for most
of my life. This kind of background has got me thinking about how AI
could affect these fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already seen multiple interdisciplinary works mixing artificial
intelligence with various art forms, like drawings, paintings, music
etc. Already drawings and paintings generated with AI present a superb
quality in those, in which you cannot make a clear distinction from if
these were created by AI or a real human. On the other hand, music is
not quite at that level yet, at least in my opinion. At least in the
form of an entirely generated song by AI. That being said, I have heard
great pieces which utilize both human touch and AI, where AI plays more
of a supportive role in the whole work. Similar things can be seen in
all the forms of creative endeavours where AI could be utilized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If AI gets used more and more in these creative projects with great
success, to me, it raises a question, can human art be entirely replaced
with AI? I believe it would be naive to say that it couldn&amp;rsquo;t. Especially
thinking about the possible future where we cannot distinguish humans
from computers, how we could distinct this kind of smaller medium like
song or book on how it was created or who created it? As a consumer of
these kinds of mediums, does it matter if some algorithms made your new
favourite novel if it can provide the same feeling that you might get
from reading a regular author&amp;rsquo;s book?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;they-are-taking-our-jobs&#34;&gt;They Are Taking Our Jobs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it shortly, AI can replace anyone&amp;rsquo;s job who happens to handle
bits in one way or another. This means that in these kinds of jobs, AI
can do it way better than you ever can. When we talk about &amp;ldquo;creative
jobs&amp;rdquo;, how you can do it better than someone else? Are you possibly
better at drawing than someone else? Or can you compose better
symphonies than someone else? What makes you better? Is it purely a
technical thing, or is there something else? When we talk about painting
or drawing&amp;rsquo;s technicality, sure, you could argue that your &amp;ldquo;pen
strokes&amp;rdquo;, etc. might be better than someone else&amp;rsquo;s. But does this make
it better art?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already there has been a trend of AI-generated music populating
different streaming platforms. Currently, that music has almost always
been something simple, in which AI definitely can excel. This could be
called elevator music or Muzak. This kind of music is most likely
something that many people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind that it&amp;rsquo;s generated with
computer and lacks the human touch. But how people would feel if there
would be a chart-topping song that was entirely generated with AI? I
believe many people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t like that, other than a few tech geeks who
might think it could be cool (me included).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could then AI fully replace the human touch in our art forms? We might
wait for that to happen for a very long time. Still, as I said earlier,
it would be naive to think that this couldn&amp;rsquo;t happen, especially in the
future, where we have reached a certain level of intelligence where we
can&amp;rsquo;t distinguish each other from humans and machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what could this mean for our &amp;ldquo;blue-collar&amp;rdquo; artists? What could be the
driving force for them to create new art if the possible audience
doesn&amp;rsquo;t know if it was created by computer or human? To me, that seems
very grim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;creative-programming&#34;&gt;Creative Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can&amp;rsquo;t beat them, join &amp;lsquo;em? Right? If we think that this will be
the future, while it might not be a very uplifting thing to consider,
it&amp;rsquo;ll most likely be very realistic. While I think that AI will have
some bad repercussions on our life in the future, I also believe that it
can be used for great good. Whether AI is used in health, fighting
climate change etc., there are many good use cases. In my opinion,
utilizing AI in the arts is also one of them. Should you create your
next song or novel entirely with AI? Possibly no, although GPT-3 has
shown some great results on how good text it can write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally at least like to write or play music, so I don&amp;rsquo;t want to
replace the process that I enjoy so much with something artificial. So
the way I could utilize it in my creative endeavours is by working with
it side by side. Possibly, it could generate some ideas for me for my
next blog post, novel, poem or whatever. AI could be taught with the
text of a long list of your favourite authors or songs by your favourite
bands. Based on this knowledge, maybe some of the possible ideas it
could generate could then be finished by a human giving the final piece
that human touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while the future might look dark and grim for us, maybe we could make
some use of it, so at least we might have a little bit of
enjoyment. Thankfully we are a long way from this singularity that many
people tend to talk about, but the trend has shown to be moving towards
that kind of future. So rather than fighting against it, at least
personally, I want to make the best use of our technical achievements in
one way or another. Who knows if the next big novel or piece is created
along with AI or some other great technological invention. That being
said, I have already found many great ways to utilize AI in my creative
projects, so who knows what might come out of those.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Reading</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/code-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 19:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/code-reading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Code reading has always been this activity that I&amp;rsquo;ve just done without
really giving any thought to it. But despite this, now, when I look back
at this habit, I see it is immensely beneficial. This habit caught my
attention when I was reading Peter Seibel&amp;rsquo;s book Coders at Work, in
which there is a section where Peter asks about code reading from his
interviewees. It tended to be unanimous amongst his interviewees that
code reading is very beneficial. Still, while reading his interviews, it
left a picture that even within those heavyweight programmers, the
practice itself seemed to be lacking. Exception in this being Brad
Fitzpatrick and, obviously, Donald Knuth. If these kinds of programmers
speak for this practice but don&amp;rsquo;t do it in the wild, then who does? This
overall, it seems pretty odd to me. Seibel made a great comparison
regarding this when he compared programmers to novelists, where if
novelist hasn&amp;rsquo;t read anyone else&amp;rsquo;s publications, it would be unheard
of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always enjoyed reading others&#39; source code mainly, let&amp;rsquo;s face it,
to steal some ideas. But doing this, I&amp;rsquo;ve able to receive a long list of
different lessons, ideas, and patterns, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to utilize
frequently in most of the work that I&amp;rsquo;ve done after these revelations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pattern-matching&#34;&gt;Pattern Matching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant benefits that I&amp;rsquo;ve learned while code
reading is that you&amp;rsquo;re able to learn various patterns after a
while. Sure, every project might seem cluttered and hard to understand
for a while, but when you get the gist of it, you start to realize why
this or that has been done the way it is. When you&amp;rsquo;ve understood some of
these patterns, it gets much more comfortable to start noticing them in
other similar or not so similar projects. Fundamentally this means the
graph of WTF-per-seconds starts getting less and less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also noticed that this kind of pattern matching helps understand
the whole project under study itself. It would be best if you didn&amp;rsquo;t try
to comprehend a large open-source project at once but in small
pieces. When one of these pieces is understood, it can help tremendously
in understanding the other pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits-of-reinventing&#34;&gt;Benefits of reinventing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, quite often, it can be pretty hard to understand the functionality
of some part of a big program just by looking at the code. So quite
often, to get a better grasp of foreign code is to reimplement the way
you would write it. This way, you&amp;rsquo;re able to abstract the bread and
butter out of the program and utilize it however you might want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of reimplementing can be quite hard on bigger projects. The
best way to reinvent something in those projects is to change something
and see changes in the new compilation. For example, try to change some
text in some menu or output. This way, you can easily test how well you
understand the foreign code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-as-a-literature-medium&#34;&gt;Code as a literature medium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people tend to say that code is not literature because you read it
differently than prose. In my opinion, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to
be the case. Overall, code is written for humans first and then machine
second. An excellent example of this is Robert C. Martin&amp;rsquo;s ravings, in
which he often recites that the &amp;ldquo;code should read like prose to be
clean&amp;rdquo;, which I tend to agree with. Another good one is Donald Knuth&amp;rsquo;s
approach with literate programming. However, the latter one is more
about embedding code pieces amidst what one could call
prose. Nonetheless, this kind of system makes the code much more
readable since the writing itself is such a big part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that I believe makes people think code is not literature is
syntax highlighting. I don&amp;rsquo;t use it. For some reason, I never grow used
to colored text. Of course, I might be a little bit biased, but when I
turn on syntax highlighting, I tend to focus on the wrong things in the
code, making it so that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t read like prose anymore. Removing
syntax highlighting has allowed me to get a better grasp of the whole
structure more easily. Is this true, or does it work for everyone? I
don&amp;rsquo;t think so, but that&amp;rsquo;s how I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-reading-club&#34;&gt;Code Reading Club&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these thoughts and Seibel&amp;rsquo;s ideas, I decided to give some sort
of code reading club a try in my workplace. Initially, what I had in
mind for this kind of club was choosing one library/program per
week/month or whatever and then dissect the main logic behind it and
discuss it. I quickly realized that this would most likely work since
people have different interests in programming. For example, I don&amp;rsquo;t
have an interest in various GUI applications or other frontend
technologies, even though they might have some good ideas behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a much better approach would most likely be that person chooses one
library/program and then dissects it sharing the findings to the rest of
the group. This dissection done by someone else than yourself could
easily inspire you and others to dive more deeply into the code itself,
even though it might be a little bit outside your interests. That being
said, exploring the world around your circles can be mind-opening since
you can easily find new approaches to the same problems that you might
face in your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to give this kind of approach a good try, and I could write some
&amp;ldquo;deep thoughts&amp;rdquo; about it in the form of a review.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extravagancy in Tech</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/extravagancy-in-tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 17:16:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/extravagancy-in-tech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve lately started to ponder the repercussions of this trend of
extravagant architectural choices in the tech industry. Mostly these
kinds of options seem to be prevalent in this current era of cloud
computing. At least, I seem to stumble upon these regularly when I work
with a wide variety of different distributed systems as a DevOps/SRE
consultant. Great examples in this kind of trend are various Kubernetes
setups in projects where you could easily manage to progress without it
or some data infrastructure solution that feels like a sledgehammer for
hitting a small nail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not bashing these technologies since I enjoy working with them, and
I work with them daily. They have their purpose, but quite often, this
purpose is meant for a way larger picture in mind. Now, if we focus on
the example of Kubernetes, sure, it can bring a lot of benefits, like
easier deployments, reducing complexity on large projects, and quite
often reducing costs. But no one can argue that it can be overkill in
many different projects. If it&amp;rsquo;s not needed, it mainly brings
unnecessary complexity and reduces productivity in these projects. So it
can be a double-edged sword. But I don&amp;rsquo;t want to focus on these singular
technologies in this topic since they feel minor on the grand scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;implications-on-our-evolution&#34;&gt;Implications on our evolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are moving more and more to this science-fiction picture of the
future, we need to start thinking more about topics such as
transhumanism and how we are going to live with machines that&amp;rsquo;ll
outsmart us. Understandably, topics associated with transhumanism, like
singularity, AI, nanotechnologies, cybernetics, and much more, are
challenging to discuss first of all on a technological level and but
also on a moral and ethical level. It is also hard to say that will we
even ever see the rise of these kinds of technologies. It could be that
our civilization can see that these inventions are possible, but we
cannot implement these. It could also be that technological evolution
has also started to get so rapid that we will see the big turn of events
in these topics in the near future. Overall &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kurzweilai.net/the-law-of-accelerating-returns&#34;&gt;technological evolution grows exponentially&lt;/a&gt;,
so the time between significant inventions gets shorter and shorter.
So, for now, we can only speculate on how things might turn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the outcome may be, I believe that some degree of optimism is
in place. I think the singularity is inevitable, and most of the
industry&amp;rsquo;s actions indicate that the path is not towards good. These
actions are the main reason why these over-the-top architectural choices
might be hinting about something that might be inevitably bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I talk about some projects using these &amp;ldquo;sledgehammer&amp;rdquo; solutions in
projects where they aren&amp;rsquo;t necessary, I&amp;rsquo;m overall talking about a small
pesky thing. What worries me about this topic is that we are using these
kinds of hyped-up tools, which happens to be the month&amp;rsquo;s flavor in every
project; what could this mean, for example, in the development of AI or
other future technologies? Could the fact that we seem to have endless
resources cause something that cannot be reverted? &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2000/04/joy-2/&#34;&gt;Bill Joy wrote a
great essay about the future not needing us&lt;/a&gt;,
which makes it scary to think that we run these extravagant systems just
mainly because we can. A similar thing applies to data collection and
many other issues in privacy. Most of the big platforms that utilize
some tracking tends to collect a lot of data, which quite often isn&amp;rsquo;t
used thoroughly, so the data is collected to build minimal information
about the user. Possibly the rest are saved for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;smart-usage-of-limited-resources&#34;&gt;Smart usage of limited resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the olden days, when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even born, computers tended to be
understandably very limited in terms of resources. Computing has evolved
tremendously since allowing us to use these kinds of larger-than-life
solutions in environments where they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be
needed. Now, has the quality of systems or programs evolved directly
proportional to the increase of computing power? Definitely not. The
fact that these kinds of powers are available to us everywhere has
possibly increased the number of innovations since more people can start
thinking possible uses for these machines that are all around us and
because they are in contact with them regularly. Although you could
think that since more people are in contact with these kinds of machines
daily that it would equal to more interest in programming etc. as
general. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where I&amp;rsquo;m getting with this is the fact that the quality tends to be
going down when we go towards the future; how could this be tackled?
Clearly, this kind of wild west design in these kinds of crucial systems
can&amp;rsquo;t continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;strategic-approach-in-the-development&#34;&gt;Strategic approach in the development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are talking about this extravagancy phenomenon in tech projects,
it tends to affect the program/system developers the most. Often, they
are not making these decisions since, most of the time, it tends to be
someone from the ivory tower that plans these decisions. Thankfully,
these kinds of people tend to have at least some background in these
systems relatively frequently but not always. So should developer&amp;rsquo;s
opinions matter more when thinking of various options for your project?
I believe Sun Microsystems had a great idea when they started to market
Java for people. Sun was a hardware company that figured out that to
sell more hardware, they had to please programmers first, which resulted
in Java being one of the most widely used languages today. Now, did Java
please programmers, maybe back then when people hated C++, but opinions
seem to have shifted in recent years,  although both languages still
enjoy immense support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think these large systems have their places in many domains,
but these domains where their power could use efficiently are very
rare. This ends up in a situation where we either have a lot of
unnecessary computing power just laying there or used for something
unnecessary. Now systems have this unnecessary complexity that mainly
hinders the workflow of the people developing the whole system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think that doing something for the reason of &amp;ldquo;this might be
needed in the future&amp;rdquo; is a bad practice since this tends to end up in an
infinite loop of unnecessary work. Since more straightforward solutions
tend to be quite often good enough for most of the projects with much
better developer experience and much better efficiency. These kinds of
solutions also quite often allow effortless migration to a bigger and
better solution if it&amp;rsquo;s needed. Don&amp;rsquo;t optimize if it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contemplating Web Analytics</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/contemplating-web-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 20:25:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/contemplating-web-analytics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started to rekindle my, unfortunately, lost writing habit a couple of
weeks ago. I set up Google Analytics for this page mainly due to its
ease of use to see simple analytics. I was only interested in visitor
count and possibly from what source my readers are coming. Google
Analytics is a massive tool with massive amounts of data going into
it. I tried to restrict this collection as much as possible so it suits
my personal blog&amp;rsquo;s needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then my page rose to the front page of Hacker News, and it started to
get a lot of traction. Suddenly there were thousands of readers coming
every day to my pesky little page with just a few posts as I was
following the visitor counts rising in my Google Analytics view. That
got me thinking about the ethics of this kind of tracking. Which then
ended up me deleting my account and data from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;discomfort-of-tracking&#34;&gt;Discomfort of Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I deleted my data and account from Google Analytics, I first
looked for different alternatives. I stumbled upon many other
privacy-oriented and GDPR-compliant analytics platforms, which at first
seemed promising. Also, having good options for ever prevalent Google
Analytics is a great thing. But despite these features, they don&amp;rsquo;t
remove the uneasiness what mining your users&#39; data causes. We are
talking about spying here. Thankfully there are now some restrictions
regarding personally identifiable information (PII), at least in the
GDPR, limiting the shadiness of this quite a lot. But that brings new
issues in handling this kind of information since you need to be sure
that your software doesn&amp;rsquo;t leak this information. Thankfully also
opting-out completely from collecting PII in your software is an
option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand why people might want to add at least simplistic tracking
to their sites since it can provide useful information about your
content, and companies can see how users use their site, and the list
goes on. Especially when you combine Google Analytics, or similar
analytics tool, to ads, companies can reap significant benefits from
this kind of tracking. But 9 of 10 sites shouldn&amp;rsquo;t need this. You could
argue that most administrators use this tracking only for dopamine fix
and don&amp;rsquo;t utilize the tracked data. Even though they might use it
somehow, how they inform the user? I dare to say that information about
data usage is almost always written in some shallow boilerplate text or
no way at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;informed-consent&#34;&gt;Informed Consent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gdpr-info.eu/&#34;&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; highlights mainly four things about data usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It enables EU citizens to have the final say on how their data is used.
If your company any way handles PIIs, there are tighter restrictions
on how these can be handled.
Companies can store/use data only if the person consents to it.
User has rights to their data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consent is the crucial part here since I believe that many sites lack on
this front. There has been a lot of discussion about what should is
considered consent. &lt;a href=&#34;https://gdpr-info.eu/art-6-gdpr/&#34;&gt;GDPR Art. 6.1(f)&lt;/a&gt;
says that &amp;ldquo;processing is necessary for the purposes of the legitimate
interests pursued by the controller or by a third party&amp;rdquo;. Now legitimate
interest is relatively shallow and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dataguidance.com/news/germany-dpas-issue-statements-consent-cookies-and-google-analytics%C2%A0&#34;&gt;quite a few authorities in Germany,
for example, consider that third-party analytics do not fall under
&amp;ldquo;legitimate
interest&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. You
can utilize consent management platforms to ensure you have user&amp;rsquo;s
consent before you drop the tracking code in your page. But this then
raises the question of what can be considered consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drew DeVault wrote a great post about &lt;a href=&#34;https://drewdevault.com/2020/12/04/Analytics-and-informed-consent.html&#34;&gt;web analytics and informed
consent&lt;/a&gt;. Informed
consent is a principle from healthcare, but it still can offer
significant elements to be utilized, especially in technology and
privacy. Drew split up the essential elements of informed consent in
tracking to these three points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disclosure of the nature and purpose of the research and its
implications (risks and benefits) for the participant, and the
confidentiality of the collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An adequate understanding of these facts on the part of the
participant, requiring an accessible explanation in lay terms and an
assessment of understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The participant must exercise voluntary agreement, without coercion or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fear of repercussions (e.g. not being allowed to use your website).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering these essential elements of informed consent, we can agree
that most sites that do tracking don&amp;rsquo;t follow these guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully trivial tracker blocking is supported already in many
browsers, which makes this issue slightly more bearable, and also,
you&amp;rsquo;re able to download external tools to do it. But still, this kind of
approach is pretty upside down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-kinds-of-cookies&#34;&gt;All Kinds of Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, ad-tech companies have tried to make blocking these
harder and harder by constantly evolving these cookies to &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.sophos.com/en-us/security-news/2019/supercookies.aspx&#34;&gt;evercookies,
supercookies,
etc.&lt;/a&gt;
The way these have worked is that trackers have stored these harder to
detect and delete cookies in different obscure places in the browser,
like Flash storage or HSTS flags. Evercookies were a big thing in early
2010 since many sites were using Flash and Silverlight, and those were
very exploitable. Today those technologies aren&amp;rsquo;t used anymore, but that
doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the evolution of cookies has stopped. Supercookies, on the
other hand, work on the network level of your service provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully lately, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.mozilla.org/security/2021/01/26/supercookie-protections/&#34;&gt;Firefox has been able to start tackling
these&lt;/a&gt;. In
that post, the Firefox team discloses what they had to do to take some
actions against this, and it is wild. They had to re-architect the whole
connection handling in the browser, which was first made to increase
user experience by reducing overhead to eliminate these pesky
cache-based cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.sophos.com/en-us/security-news/2019/supercookies.aspx&#34;&gt;browser
fingerprinting&lt;/a&gt;
could be considered the evilest cookie of them all. Browser
fingerprinting identifies everything it can from your system. Like some
cookies, this does have some real use cases, e.g., preventing fraud in
financial institutions. Still, mostly this is just another intrusive way
to track people. Thankfully some modern browsers offer at least some
ways to avoid this, but not a full-fledged solution (other than
disposable systems).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-of-cookies&#34;&gt;Future of cookies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.axios.com/google-privacy-friendly-substitute-cookies-test-05c2c28e-77f1-4921-9a99-1ef0c009b064.html&#34;&gt;Lately, there has been some news about privacy-friendly substitutes to
cookies by tech
giants.&lt;/a&gt;
Cookies have been a relatively significant issue privacy-wise for
decades, and since the ad industry is so large, finding a replacement
for these have been hard. So only time will tell. I believe that we
cannot get rid of cookies entirely in the near future. They might change
into something else, maybe this kind of API utilizing machine learning
analyzing user data. Which I don&amp;rsquo;t know is better or worse. So cannot
wait! &lt;em&gt;tin-foil hat tightens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the conclusion here? Probably nothing. Recently started
small-time blogger just got scared from big numbers coming into his site
collecting all kinds of data which ended up him stopping this kind of
action at least in his site. Since for most users/sites, this kind of
tracking is just a silly monkey-get-banana dopamine fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t track unless you need to and if you do, inform it thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leap of Faith in Email Providers</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 13:35:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When talking about the tools of the trade, almost regardless of the
industry, email seems to be a vital tool. The same applies to
me. Obviously, in the tech industry, everything goes by email. But also
in music. If I happen to record, mix or master something, pretty much
always these are shared with email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email is also a crucial part of my workflow, so I care about my
productivity while using it. Recently I started to look for options for
my two different GSuite accounts. One of those was used for my personal
domain, and another one was used for my music publishing company. A big
reason behind the migration was that I found GSuite to be a little bit
too much for my needs. I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have anything against
Google&amp;rsquo;s product, albeit I agree they have a little bit too big of a
footprint on the internet, so I at least try to limit my contributions
to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements-for-provider&#34;&gt;Requirements for Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only have two requirements for my provider: IMAP/SMTP support and the
ability to use my domain(s). Given these requirements, there are
probably hundreds of providers that would fit these requirements. But
after a while of skimming through different providers, I ended up with
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastmail.com/&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://protonmail.com/&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fastmail&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail seemed like a good fit when I first looked into it. Easily
manageable domains and reasonable pricing. I quickly tested it with
their offered trial account and was overall pretty pleased with their
product. Concerns about this then rose when I learned that the company
is from Australia. Not that I hate Australia by any means, but their
hostile and subversive laws regarding encryption are pretty sketchy. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.homeaffairs.gov.au/about-us/our-portfolios/national-security/lawful-access-telecommunications/data-encryption&#34;&gt;The
assistance and access
act&lt;/a&gt;
allows, under Australia&amp;rsquo;s legislation, police to force companies to
create a technical function that would give them access to encrypted
messages without the user&amp;rsquo;s knowledge, which made FastMail pretty much a
no-go for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protonmail&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finding Australia&amp;rsquo;s laws against encryption, it seemed like a
natural choice. I had already heard of them before and their stand on
security. ProtonMail doesn&amp;rsquo;t support IMAP/SMTP access, at least in the
standard way, mainly because of encryption, which is why I didn&amp;rsquo;t want
to go that route when I first heard of them. Nowadays, they do offer a
kind of unorthodox solution for this via their ProtonMail Bridge. By my
understanding, this only handles the authentication to your mail and
provider localhost-only endpoints to IMAP4/SMTP. Then you can configure
your mail client of choice with these new endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting solution, and at least for me, it seems to work and doesn&amp;rsquo;t
hinder my workflow that much. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy
with their product and decided to migrate my emails to there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;honorable-mention-migadu&#34;&gt;Honorable Mention: Migadu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.migadu.com/index.html&#34;&gt;Migadu&lt;/a&gt;
Migadu is on the smaller end of the spectrum when talking about email
providers, but overall they seemed to have great values. Why I didn&amp;rsquo;t go
that route (yet?) is that I read that they have had some outages in
their services in the past. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that your email has been
lost since the global mail system is pretty tolerant for that, but not
being able to login into your mail, which can be pretty annoying. What
made them not very suitable for me is their bandwidth-based pricing and
daily limits on mail. I do work a lot with email and send and receive a
lot of them, so they did offer pricing suitable for my needs, but it
just was a little bit too expensive at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dishonorable-mention-self-hosting&#34;&gt;Dishonorable Mention: Self-hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail at first seemed like a good fit, but due to Australia&amp;rsquo;s
legislation, it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me. ProtonMail overall seems like
a pretty exciting provider, at least on paper and overall in practice too.
Service seemed to suite me, so I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to use their service at
least for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reawakening Long Lost Habit (or Forming a New One)</title>
      <link>https://topikettunen.com/posts/reawakening-long-lost-habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 18:03:57 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://topikettunen.com/posts/reawakening-long-lost-habit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I had a good habit of writing semi-regularly about
various exciting topics. Unfortunately, time passed, and I began to write less
and less, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten out of the habit altogether. This is a shame
in many ways since I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt writing to be immensely therapeutic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, this world is also in a very odd place. Most of the
countries worldwide are quarantined due to COVID-19, and people are staying in
their homes. Yours truly included! So as a way to pass the the time during these
times, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to reawaken this habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Habitual writing has been on my mind for a long time, especially since it has
been so present in my life before. I&amp;rsquo;ve also somehow lost a few other healthy
habits, which lately have made me think about how I can reawaken them in my
day-to-day life. Healthy practices that come to mind that I&amp;rsquo;ve lost would
definitely be workouts and meditation. Although you could argue that the lost
habit of working out is mainly related to the current difficult times, I&amp;rsquo;m not
too worried. That I believe that eventually, when the world calms down in terms
of this pandemic, I can relearn that habit quite quickly. But losing the regular
practice of meditation is really a shame, in my opinion. Similar to working out,
meditation has been playing a big part in my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though my meditation practices have been irregular lately, the earlier
&amp;ldquo;hard work&amp;rdquo; has definitely helped me in my everyday life. But recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve
started thinking about how I could relearn this habit. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that at
least in my own case best way to learn habit has definitely been doing something
often but not in an excessive amount. So in meditation, this was easy. Start by
5 or 10 minutes (which is nothing, and everyone can find time for this) and just
do it the same time and place every day. Current times supported in relearning
this since people are mostly working remotely, so it is easy to start your day
with this practice. With these simple steps, I feel like that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to
reawaken this practice that was once very present in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking about utilizing a similar approach in some other practices
that I&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten. The practices that came to mind were music and
writing. Although some could argue that these are more or less the same
thing. For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a real hard time picking up my instruments and
writing some new music during the pandemic. I believe that many others have the
same feelings in their own area of interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the cause for this;
maybe the constant staring at the same four walls for over a year is the
culprit. Who knows? A similar thing has also happened in my writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really got me wanting to reawaken these habits was when I stumbled upon
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dreamsongs.com/Bio.html&#34;&gt;Richard P. Gabriel&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; poetry. Gabriel is a
legendary Lisp programmer. As a Lisp programmer myself, I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in
what other like-minded people are up to. Gabriel started a project of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dreamsongs.com/DailyPoems.html&#34;&gt;writing
one poem a day on March 18, 2000&lt;/a&gt; to
end a lengthy poetry-writing slump. Gabriel agrees that he is not necessarily a
great poet, even though many could argue that, but I think that is
non-essential. While forming this kind of habit, you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to
be the new Robert Frost. But since writing poetry (or anything) is a technical
skill, constant practice is bound to help you in your journey. I stumbled upon a
similar approach while reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Writing-Better-Lyrics-Pat-Pattison/dp/1582975779&#34;&gt;Pat Pattison&amp;rsquo;s Writing Better
Lyrics&lt;/a&gt;,
where he talked about &amp;ldquo;daily object writing&amp;rdquo; in terms of getting better at
writing. Pattison also noted that forming a habit is the big thing in this,
which will eventually result in getting better at writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach is more or less similar to how I learned the healthy habit of
regular meditation. How could I apply a similar approach to my composing and
writing? Knowing myself, I cannot do this kind of creative work sporadically (or
waiting for the creative slump to end), or I&amp;rsquo;ll never do it. If I tried to write
one piece and post every day, I feel that doing both daily would be a little bit
excessive (mainly timewise). So I need to find a healthy balance in practice and
not making it over-encumbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I believe that some time-boxed, very focused practice on something
works the best. So what I&amp;rsquo;m intending to do is that I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on a period (half
an hour, an hour or so) on the given task, whether it is composing, writing, or
programming (another healthy habit that I practice which thankfully haven&amp;rsquo;t been
lost, but I always feel I could do more of it). I&amp;rsquo;ll set a healthy goal for this
time-box, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to write some new groundbreaking sonata, some
earth-shattering blog post, or the next big open source project. I&amp;rsquo;ll just want
to do something in these fields regularly to hone my skills in the given area. I
also understand that since I&amp;rsquo;m trying to work on multiple habits, I might not
always have time to do everything. That&amp;rsquo;s okay. I can most likely squeeze in a
smaller session so that you have at least some practice. Or if I just simply
cannot do anything, that&amp;rsquo;s fine too. I just don&amp;rsquo;t want to see myself doing
something excessively one day and then slacking off the next day since &amp;ldquo;I did so
much yesterday&amp;rdquo; (learned from Pattison).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity overall has been really close to my heart, even though I
occasionally lack significantly in that area. But maybe with small steps,
everyone can benefit somehow in a slight boost of their own productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or just procrastinate&amp;hellip; As long as you&amp;rsquo;re happy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
