<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>migadu on Cogitations of Topi</title>
    <link>https://kettunen.io/tags/migadu.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in migadu on Cogitations of Topi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Except as noted, this work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 13:35:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kettunen.io/tags/migadu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Leap of Faith in Email Providers</title>
      <link>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/24/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 13:35:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kettunen.io/2021/01/24/leap-of-faith-in-email-providers.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When talking about the tools of the trade, almost regardless of the
industry, email seems to be a vital tool. The same applies to
me. Obviously, in the tech industry, everything goes by email. But also
in music. If I happen to record, mix or master something, pretty much
always these are shared with email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email is also a crucial part of my workflow, so I care about my
productivity while using it. Recently I started to look for options for
my two different GSuite accounts. One of those was used for my personal
domain, and another one was used for my music publishing company. A big
reason behind the migration was that I found GSuite to be a little bit
too much for my needs. I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have anything against
Google&amp;rsquo;s product, albeit I agree they have a little bit too big of a
footprint on the internet, so I at least try to limit my contributions
to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements-for-provider&#34;&gt;Requirements for Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only have two requirements for my provider: IMAP/SMTP support and the
ability to use my domain(s). Given these requirements, there are
probably hundreds of providers that would fit these requirements. But
after a while of skimming through different providers, I ended up with
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastmail.com/&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://protonmail.com/&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fastmail&#34;&gt;FastMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail seemed like a good fit when I first looked into it. Easily
manageable domains and reasonable pricing. I quickly tested it with
their offered trial account and was overall pretty pleased with their
product. Concerns about this then rose when I learned that the company
is from Australia. Not that I hate Australia by any means, but their
hostile and subversive laws regarding encryption are pretty sketchy.&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.homeaffairs.gov.au/about-us/our-portfolios/national-security/lawful-access-telecommunications/data-encryption&#34;&gt;The
assistance and access
act&lt;/a&gt;
allows, under Australia&amp;rsquo;s legislation, police to force companies to
create a technical function that would give them access to encrypted
messages without the user&amp;rsquo;s knowledge, which made FastMail pretty much a
no-go for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protonmail&#34;&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finding Australia&amp;rsquo;s laws against encryption, it seemed like a
natural choice. I had already heard of them before and their stand on
security. ProtonMail doesn&amp;rsquo;t support IMAP/SMTP access, at least in the
standard way, mainly because of encryption, which is why I didn&amp;rsquo;t want
to go that route when I first heard of them. Nowadays, they do offer a
kind of unorthodox solution for this via their ProtonMail Bridge. By my
understanding, this only handles the authentication to your mail and
provider localhost-only endpoints to IMAP4/SMTP. Then you can configure
your mail client of choice with these new endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting solution, and at least for me, it seems to work and doesn&amp;rsquo;t
hinder my workflow that much. Still, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy
with their product and decided to migrate my emails to there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;honorable-mention-migadu&#34;&gt;Honorable Mention: Migadu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.migadu.com/index.html&#34;&gt;Migadu&lt;/a&gt;
Migadu is on the smaller end of the spectrum when talking about email
providers, but overall they seemed to have great values. Why I didn&amp;rsquo;t go
that route (yet?) is that I read that they have had some outages in
their services in the past. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that your email has been
lost since the global mail system is pretty tolerant for that, but not
being able to login into your mail, which can be pretty annoying. What
made them not very suitable for me is their bandwidth-based pricing and
daily limits on mail. I do work a lot with email and send and receive a
lot of them, so they did offer pricing suitable for my needs, but it
just was a little bit too expensive at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dishonorable-mention-self-hosting&#34;&gt;Dishonorable Mention: Self-hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FastMail at first seemed like a good fit, but due to Australia&amp;rsquo;s
legislation, it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me. ProtonMail overall seems like
a pretty exciting provider, at least on paper and overall in practice too.
Service seemed to suite me, so I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to use their service at
least for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
